Well, here's where I tell you that about
5 minutes after the peace treaty ending
World War II was signed, a new global
conflict known as the Cold War erupted.
And I reckon it's time we talked about
it. So, if you're ready to get them
brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay, so let's start as is proper by
trying to understand what in the fresh
heck a Cold War is in the first place.
So, by definition, a Cold War describes
a state of hostility that exists between
two opposing governments chiefly
characterized by an ideological struggle
rather than open warfare. So, that's a
Cold War, but when we talk about the
Cold War in this unit, we're talking
about a very specific decades-long
conflict between two very specific
global powers, namely the United States
and the Soviet Union. And we'll talk all
about that hostility in the rest of the
video, but for now, let me just give you
an overview of the ideological struggle
between these two nations. And that
struggle in its simplest form is this:
The United States represented democratic
capitalism, which emphasized free market
economics and political participation
from citizens. But the Soviet Union
represented authoritarian communism,
which emphasized strict government
control of the economy and the
redistribution of wealth equally to all
citizens who essentially had no voice in
the government. And it's not hard to
understand why these two worldviews were
entirely antagonistic and incompatible.
But what's not as clear as why those two
ideologies had to create an entire
stinking Cold War that took over
everyone's crap for like 40 years. Like,
couldn't the United States just stay
over there and do its democratic thing
while the Soviets had their communist
party over there? And not really, and
here's why. You see, both of these
ideologies are universalizing ideas,
meaning that those who hold them want
everyone else to hold them as well. So,
the US wasn't satisfied to keep
democracy to themselves, nor were the
Soviets satisfied to keep communism to
themselves. Each ideology could only
prove its superior worth once every
square inch of the dang planet was
conformed to one ideology or the other.
And more to the point, the spread of one
ideology was a threat to the existence
of the other ideology, so, you know,
Cold War. Anyway, this conflict pretty
much dominated domestic and global
affairs for much of the second half of
the 20th century. In other words, no
matter what political or cultural or
economic development we could talk about
from 1945 to 1980, the Cold War was all
over. And I know your brain matter is
eagerly twitching with excitement to
figure out the causes of this conflict,
but I need to pause and acknowledge that
the A push national exam is rapidly
approaching. And if you need help
getting a five on that sweet bippy, then
you might want to check out my A push
Heimler review guide, which is the
fastest way to study. And if that's
something you're into, you can check the
link in the description. All right, now
let's move along to the causes of the
Cold War, and I'm going to give you one
long-term cause and two short-term
causes. So, the long-term cause of the
tension between the United States and
the Soviet Union began during the
Russian Revolution, which transformed
Russia into a proper communist state.
And once that transformation was
complete, US policymakers went ahead and
thumbed their nose at the Soviet Union
by refusing to extend diplomatic
recognition of the new state. And it
even went beyond nose thumbing when the
United States sent troops to help
support the anti-Bolshevik forces
fighting against the communists. And so,
all of that combined meant that the
Soviets were more than a little saucy
when it came to the United States. But
then also remember what we talked about
in unit seven, namely the Red Scare
during the 1920s. See, none of that
opposition I just mentioned to the
formation of a communist state actually
was successful, and that worked up a
nice lather of flop sweat on American
policymakers. And in response to said
flop sweat, policymakers kicked up the
Red Scare, which was an attempt to
entirely remove all communists from the
American population. So, yeah, lots of
tension had been building up for
decades. But now let's consider two
short-term causes for the Cold War.
First of all, the Americans and Soviets
deeply disagreed about the post-war
future of Germany and several Eastern
European countries. So, Joseph Stalin
viewed these countries, which the Soviet
military had liberated from German
occupation, as states that ought to
remain under Soviet control and act as a
buffer zone against any future German
aggression. But Harry Truman and
Roosevelt before him pushed for these
countries to become independent and
democratic. And to be fair, in the
beginning both parties did agree to free
elections in Eastern Europe, but over
time it became clear that Stalin had no
intention of honoring that agreement,
not least in Soviet troops already
occupied those countries after the war.
And my goodness, did that get Truman in
a proper Midwestern sulk, complete with
a devastating finger wag. But I should
point out that there was no small amount
of hypocrisy in Truman wagging his
finger at Stalin for doing this. After
all, as Henry Wallace, Truman's own
Secretary of Commerce, pointed out, the
United States has essentially done the
same thing by advancing policies to
control its own sphere of influence in
Latin America. Anyway, the second
short-term cause of the Cold War had to
do with growing tension around nuclear
weapons. First of all, Stalin was sore
over the fact that the US, supposedly an
ally during the war, had kept this
technology a secret from the Soviets.
However, to be fair, Stalin definitely
knew about the atomic bomb before its
deployment because Soviet intelligence
had already discovered the project. But
whatever, neither Roosevelt nor Truman
told Stalin about it, and so mistrust
unlocked. And then second, after the
war, the Soviets called on the US to
destroy its nuclear arsenal, but the US
was like
>> [laughter]
>> This guy. This guy. But there was also a
whole lot of mistrust because the
Soviets felt they had shouldered a
disproportionate amount of combat in
World War II while the US dragged its
feet on opening a second front on the
west. And so all of that combined led to
the proper emergence of the Cold War
onto the world stage. Okay, so now that
it's on like Donkey Kong, let me tell
you about a few of the major policies
and developments that occurred as a
result of this conflict, and I will
start with the one policy to rule them
all, namely containment. So as tensions
with the Soviets grew deeper, President
Truman articulated the guiding
philosophy for US Cold War policy that
would influence events for decades.
known as containment, and it was first
articulated by a US diplomat in the
Soviet Union, namely George Kennan, and
there were two parts to this policy.
First, Kennan argued that his own
first-hand experience of Stalin's
communist regime convinced him that
Stalin intended to aggressively expand
communism throughout the world, and
therefore must be met with firm
resistance. Second, believing that no
free population would adopt communism by
choice, Kennan argued that the United
States needed to play a big role in
helping rebuild Western European
countries. In other words, as long as
those countries didn't slip into
economic distress, then they would never
be tempted to try on the svelte garments
of communism to help alleviate their
woe. And so Truman gobbled that
containment idea right up and soon
turned it into a practical set of
policies that became known as the Truman
Doctrine. And essentially it said that
the United States will provide military
and economic aid to any democratic
country threatened by the spread of
communism. And I know that containment
and the Truman Doctrine sound the same,
but containment is just the idea that
the spread of communism must be stopped
in all possible ways, and the Truman
Doctrine put the idea into practice by
throwing dollars and guns at the
problem. Okay, so now that you
understand the big idea that guided
foreign policy during the Cold War
years, let me now explain the four
developments that directly resulted from
the US embrace of containment. First,
the containment policy led the United
States to organize an alliance for
collective security. So, in 1949,
American policymakers spearheaded the
creation of NATO, also known by its
nastier name, the North Organization,
which was a military alliance between
the United States and 11 other Western
European democracies. It was an alliance
whose purpose was to resist Soviet
military expansion, and the agreement
was that an attack on one member nation
was an attack on all, and therefore all
nations would come to each other's
defense. But not to be out-allianced,
the Soviet Union went ahead and created
a rival military alliance known as the
Warsaw Pact, which included the Eastern
European nations that were within the
dominion of the Soviet Union. And then,
the second major result of containment
was an American effort to offer
international aid, and the best example
here is the Marshall Plan. $13 billion
in loans to help Western European
countries rebuild after the war, and
more to the point, to help revive their
economies. And wow, that's so nice of
the Americans. They're just a bunch of
big softies that want to help the world
become a better place with no taint of
self-interest, is what I would say on
opposite day. No, in loaning this money
to countries, US policymakers expected
two things to happen. First of all, the
growth of their economies after the
infusion of the Marshall funds would
prevent the spread of stupid communism
into their country. Second, those
countries would then be indebted to the
United States, and therefore be more
moldable to policies that favored US
interests in Europe. And then, the third
major containment-related development
you need to know is the Berlin Airlift.
So, as I mentioned earlier, one massive
honking disagreement between the United
States and the Soviets after World War
II was the future of Germany. As I
mentioned, Stalin wanted to keep Germany
weak so that it would never again pose a
threat to the Soviet Union. And you
know, you can fault this guy for a lot
of things, but this one is
understandable because Stalin had a
pocketful of receipts detailing
astonishing German aggression and
destruction from World War II. But
regardless, the US wanted to see Germany
recover its economic and political
strength in order to contribute to
Europe's overall prosperity and thus,
say it with me now, keep communism from
spreading. Now, what deeply complicated
this whole disagreement was the fact
that according to the treaty that ended
the war, Germany was divided into four
zones occupied by each of the four
Allied powers and then Berlin itself was
also divided and occupied accordingly.
And so, over here in West Germany, the
US and its allies promoted democracy and
pumped its economy full of Marshall Plan
funds in order to strengthen the
economy. But, over here in East Germany,
economy weak
and fully dependent on Soviet economic
infrastructure. And so, these rival
policies meant that East Germany and
West Germany developed much differently.
So, West Germany recovered economically
and started redeveloping its industrial
capacity at a rapid pace. But, East
Germany remained poor and underdeveloped
as a result of repressive Soviet
policies. And then, the very same
differences in policies and development
occurred in Berlin as well with the
western half prospering and growing
strong while the eastern half was broken
weak. And that was profoundly annoying
to Stalin since so many East Berliners
fled from the glories of communism that
kept them in poverty into the prosperity
of the democratic West. But, then the
real egg in Stalin's sock was the desire
of the West to introduce currency
reform, which to Stalin appeared an
effort to undermine Soviet economic
control of their own German sector. And
that is when Stalin twisted his
magnificent mustache and hatched a plan.
I mean, all you need to do is look at
this map for like 5 seconds to realize
what Stalin was about to do. Like, look
at Berlin. It's located right inside the
Soviet occupation zone of greater
Germany. And so, Stalin decided he was
going to go ahead and blockade Berlin
from further western assistance and
baby, that is how you turn up the heat
on a Cold War. But, President Truman,
unflapped by such an illegal maneuver,
authorized the Berlin Airlift in which
US and British planes dropped millions
of tons of supplies to Berliners. And it
lasted for almost a year until finally
the Soviets lifted the blockade in 1949.
And then finally, the fourth major
development that occurred as a result of
containment was a series of proxy wars,
only one of which I'm going to tell you
about here. But, first, some context.
So, one of the main features of the Cold
War was an arms race between the US and
the Soviet Union, which is to say each
side raced to build more and stronger
weapons than the other. And by the
1950s, both states had developed
hydrogen bombs, which were far more
powerful and destructive than the atomic
bombs dropped on Japan at the end of the
war. Therefore, with each nation
stockpiling such massive weapons, it
became clear that to use these bombs in
a conflict with each other would result
in mutually assured destruction. And so,
both sides knew they couldn't actually
fight each other without reducing the
entire planet into a charred pile of ash
floating through the vast nothingness of
outer space. And that was a real bummer
because they hated each other and they
really wanted to fight, but they figured
out a way to fight each other without
actually fighting each other, the proxy
war. Now, proxy, in case you don't know,
is when one thing stands in for another
thing. So, while these proxy wars had
plenty of real fighting, it was not
fighting directly between the United
States and the Soviet Union. They were
only backing other groups who aligned
with their respective ideologies in an
effort to gather more geopolitical
friends into their respective camps.
Now, the key proxy war of Truman's
administration was the Korean War, which
became a potent test case for the Truman
Doctrine in Asia. So, after World War
II, and in Korea, was divided into two
spheres of influence. The Soviet Union
supported a communist regime in the
north, while the US supported an
anti-communist government in the south.
And then in 1950, forces from the north
invaded the south in order to unite the
peninsula under a communist government.
Now, Truman, drunk on the spirits of
containment, did not ask Congress for a
declaration of war, but instead got
authorization from the United Nations to
deploy troops to defend South Korea,
although the vast majority of troops
were American. So, the fighting lasted
several years, but ultimately ended in a
stalemate with the country remaining
divided at the 38th parallel. The north
was still communist, and the south was
still anti-communist. Regardless, this
war marked a significant expansion of
executive power since Truman was able to
bypass Congress and commit troops across
the world in the name of acting as a
police power, and that's exactly how the
US got involved in another proxy war in
Vietnam, but that gets its own video.
Anyway, there's so many other Cold War
developments I could tell you about, but
we need to land the plane, and so I'll
finish by telling you this. The Cold War
lasted about four decades, and in that
time, the conflict ranged from periods
of intense conflict to periods of
detente or peace. The periods of intense
conflict included the Korean and Vietnam
Wars and a real tense couple of weeks in
1962 known as the Cuban Missile Crisis.
Long story short, during John F.
Kennedy's presidency, US intelligence
discovered Soviet missile sites being
built in Cuba. In case the full weight
of that isn't hitting you, here's Cuba,
here's the United States. So, nuclear
missiles here, mass death and
destruction here. And so, for almost 2
weeks, the tension of the Cold War
reached epic proportions since it seemed
more likely than ever that nuclear war
was about to erupt. But, ultimately, the
two nations settled the conflict through
diplomatic means rather than nuclear
war, to which I say, "Noice." But, then
there were also periods of detente as
well, the most significant occurring
during the presidency of Richard Nixon.
So, in 1972, Nixon was invited to the
Soviet Union and he became the first
American president to step foot on
Russian soil since the Cold War began.
And during that visit, Nixon worked with
Soviet leader Leonid Brezhnev to sign
the Strategic Arms Limitation Treaty, in
which both nations agreed to limit the
proliferation of nuclear weapons. And
look, there's plenty more ups and downs
in the Cold War that I'm positively
itching to tell you about, but that's
what the rest of the unit is for. Okay,
you can click here to watch all my other
Unit 8 videos, or you can click here to
grab my A Push Heimler review guide,
which has everything you need to study
as fast as possible. I'm glad you came
around, and I'll catch you on the
flip-flop. Heimler out.